这是可追溯至15世纪初期的修道院帐目
This is the monastery's account dating to the early 15th Century.
哦 跟我想的一样
Oh, precisely what I thought.
但无疑这有着巨大的政治意义
But surely this has great political significance.
所以格外的棘手
A matter of particular delicacy.
很抱歉打扰你 先生
Sorry to disturb you, sir,
但Hopkins警督想见你
but inspector Hopkins would like to see you.
前途无量的Hopkins警督
The promising Inspector Hopkins.
靠近火炉 暖和一下
Draw up to the fire and warm your toes.
希望你不会在这样一个夜晚
I hope you have no designs
给我们找事做 警督
upon us on such a night as this, inspector.
这是我的哥哥 Mycroft
This is my brother, Mycroft.
或许你们之前没见过?
Maybe you have not met before?
是的 不然我会有印象的
I'm sure, I would have remembered.
我能跟你握个手吗 先生
May I shake your hand, sir?
可以 如果你坚持的话
Yes, if you must.
Hudson夫人知道
Now Mrs. Hudson knows a prescription
一个柠檬茶的配方
containing hot water and a lemon.
我会给你弄些的 警督
I'll bring some up for you, inspector.
那对御寒很有效
It'll help keep out the chill.
谢谢你 Hudson夫人
Thank you, Mrs. Hudson.
华生医生在哪里
Where is Dr. Watson?
哦 在他的诊所里
Oh, in his surgery.
我听说 这糟糕的天气
This dreadful weather
让他的诊所外排起了长队
has produced a queue into the street I'm told.
他们在浪费时间
Well they're wasting their time.
华生用来治疗所有小病的就是
Watson's only cure for any ailment
维他命冲剂和苹果泥
is linus powder and a grated apple.
福尔摩斯先生 你知道你那样说只是
Mr. Holmes, you know you only say that
因为你想念医生
because you miss the doctor.
雪茄?
Cigar?
不 不用了 谢谢
No, no, thank you.
一定是什么重要的事
It must be something important
才让你在这暴风天气中出门
to bring you out in such a gale.
确实是
It is indeed.
你看过有关Yoxley案件的最新报道吗
Did you see anything of the  Yoxley case in the latest editions?
今天我还没看过晚于15世纪的事情
I see nothing later then the 15th Century today.
我们在研究一本500年前的手稿
We've been studying a 500-year-old palimpsest.
手稿?
Palimpsest?
别管什么15世纪了
Enough of the 15th Century,
你给我们带来了20世纪的新闻
you bring us news in the 20th.
只是一个短篇报道 但内容齐全
Well it's only a paragraph, and all wrong at that.
你应该不会错过什么
So you've not missed anything.
听到这个我就放心了 警督
I'm relieved to hear it, inspector.
事情发生在Kent
It's down in Kent,
距Chatham有7英里远
seven miles from Chatham
离铁路有3英里
and three from the railway line.
我在3:15接到报案
I was wired for at 3:15,
在5:00到达Chatham
got to Chatham at 5:00,
并展开调查
conducted my investigation,
乘最后一列火车回到Charing Cross
was back at Charing Cross by the last train
之后乘出租马车直接来到你这里
and straight to you by cab.
那意味着你对你的案子没把握
Which means you're not quite certain of your case.
那意味着我理不出一点头绪
It means I can make neither head nor tale of it.
没有作案动机 福尔摩斯先生
There's no motive, Mr. Holmes.
作案动机 警督 什么作案动机?
Motive, Inspector, what motive?
一个人死了
A man is dead,
那是毫无疑问的
there's no denying that.
但我看不出到底为什么 会有人希望他受到伤害
But I can see no reason between heaven  and earth why anyone should wish him harm.
跟我们讲讲
Tell us about it.
几年前
A few years ago
Yoxley旧居被一个老人买了下来
Yoxley Old Place was taken by an elderly man
他叫Coram教授
by the name of Professor Coram.
是个残疾人
He's an invalid,
有一半的时间待在床上
keeping his bed half the time
而剩下的另一半时间 要么是在房子里拄着拐杖
and the other half-hobbling about the house on a stick
要么就坐在轮椅上
or being pushed about the grounds by the gardener
被园丁推着
in a bath chair.
-我们到了 -你挺笨的 是不是
-Here we are. -Quite stupid, aren't you.
别着急 小心点
Now just take it easy, be very careful.
小心
Careful.
我的秘书在哪里 Marker夫人
Now where's my secretary, Mrs. Marker?
教授正在写一本学术著作
The professor is writing a learned book
在一年前他发现有必要
and found it necessary about a year ago
请一个秘书
to take on a secretary,
Willoughby Smith先生
Mr. Willoughby Smith,
一个刚从大学毕业的年轻人
a young man straight from the university.
如果一个人能接受基督一性论的学说
And if one can accept the doctrines of Monophysitism
那么他必然也会重新评价
then perforce one must also re-evaluate
基督教的宗教体系
Christian theology.
建议...
To suggest...
是的
Yes.
建议...
To suggest...
或者争论
Or to argue.
我们当中谁在写这本书
Which one of us is writing this book,
你还是我?
you, or me?
当然是您
You are, of course.
建议...
To suggest...
刚开始 Smith看起来
From the first it appears that Smith
是一个安静的受过良好教育的人
was a quiet, well-educated fellow
并且几乎没有任何缺点
with hardly any weak spot in him at all.
但就是这个年轻人
And yet this is the lad
今天早晨死在了
who met his death this morning
教授的书房里
in the professor's study
就目前情况看来只能是谋杀
under circumstances that can point only to murder.
谋杀?
Murder?
你是不是说Willoughby Smith被谋杀了 警督
Willoughby Smith was murdered you say, Inspector?
请继续
Do go on.
你的热柠檬茶 警督
Your hot lemon drink, inspector.
谢谢 Hudson夫人
Thank you Mrs. Hudson,
一个在世上没有任何敌人的人
a man without a single enemy in the world.
Hudson夫人 你又在妨碍我们
Mrs. Hudson, you're under foot again.
你说几乎没有任何缺点
When you say hardly any weak spots,
那究竟是什么意思
what exactly do you mean?
我们总会有这样那样的陋习
We all have vices of some kind or another.
Willoughby Smith没有前科
Willoughby Smith has nothing against him,
当他在Uppingham上高中
either as a boy at Uppingham
或是之后在剑桥上大学
or later as a young man at Cambridge.
但我了解到他喜欢喝酒
Although I gathered that he was fond of a drink or two.
那并不是件坏事
Well nothing wrong with that.
他也有点好色
He also had a bit of an eye for the ladies.
萝卜青菜各有所爱
Each to his own.
也许他隐瞒了一个可怕的秘密
Perhaps he was hiding a terrible secret.
Smith不认识邻里的任何人
Smith knew no one in the neighborhood
跟他的雇主过着一样的生活
and lived very much as his employer did.
教授埋首于他的创作
The professor was buried in his work
也没有别的事可做
and existed for nothing else.
跟你志趣相投啊 夏洛克
A man after your own heart, Sherlock.
除了你提过的那三个人
Apart from the three people you have mentioned,
房子里还有别的人吗
who else can be found in the house?
一个上了年纪的女管家 Marker夫人
An elderly housekeeper, Mrs. Marker,
和一个年轻的女仆 Susan Tarlton
and a young maid, Susan Tarlton.
那谁发现了尸体
So who found the body?
女仆 福尔摩斯先生
The maid, Mr. Holmes.
她说当她听见惨叫时
She said she was working in an upstairs room
她正在楼上的房间里工作
when she heard a cry.
她说当她到达书房时
She said by the time she got to the study
Smith躺在了地上 受了致命伤
Smith was lying on the floor fatally wounded.
她说
She says.
教授
Professor.
教授...教授...
The professor.
是她
It was she.
女仆发誓说
The maid is prepared to swear
这是他的原话
that those were his exact words.
教授 是她
The professor, it was she.
我画了一张草图
I've drawn up a rough plan
应该会让你对教授书房的位置 有个大体的了解
that should give you a general idea of the position of the professor's study
还包括在我看来 这个案件里各种重要的地方
and also the various points of the case which seem to me to be essential.
正如你所见
As you can see
从书房出来有两个走廊
there are two corridors which lead from the study.
一个直接通向房子的后门
One goes directly to a door at the back of the house
而另一个通向教授的卧室
and the other straight to the professor's ground floor bedroom.
两个成90度的走廊
Two corridors with a 90-degree angle
在书房外会合
joined at one end outside the study.
现在假设凶手进了房子
Now assuming the assassin entered the house,
他怎么进来的呢
how did he get in?
毫无疑问从花园的小径和后门走
Undoubtedly by the garden path and the back door,
那将直接
which gives direct access
经过走廊到达书房
via the corridor to the study.
完全正确
Exactly.
而且他必须从同一条路逃走
And he must have made his escape along the same line.
因为书房的其他两个出口
For of the two other exits from the study,
一个被女仆堵住了
one was blocked by the maid
那时她正从楼上下来
as she ran downstairs
而另一条直接通向教授的卧室
and the other goes straight to the professor's bedroom.
那凶手不能从书房的窗户逃走吗
Could not the assassin have made his escape from the study window?
-被锁上了 先生 从里面 -我明白了
-Locked sir, from within. -I see.
这对于把你的理论付诸实践
It was an excellent opportunity
是个绝佳的机会
to put your theories into practice.
我注意了一下那条
I directed my attention at once to the garden path,
被最近雨水浸洗过的花园小道
which was saturated with recent rain.
小道上没有发现脚印
No footmarks were to be found on the path
但毫无疑问
but there could be no question
有人沿着草地穿过那里
that someone had passed along the grass border, which lines it.
他这么做
And that he'd done so
是为了避免留下足迹
in order to avoid leaving a track.
你在那里发现了脚印?
You found footmarks there?
没有 但那些草被人踩过
Not exactly, but the grass was trodden down
那只会是凶手干的
and it could only have been the murderer
因为那天早晨包括园丁在内
since neither the gardener nor anyone else
没有人会出现在那个地方
had been in the area that morning
而雨是从夜里才开始的
and the rain had only begun during the night.
好极了 警督
Bravo, inspector.
我知道你会赞赏我的分析的 福尔摩斯先生
I knew you'd appreciate my reasoning, Mr. Holmes.
那些草上的足迹
These tracks in the grass,
是来的时候留下的 还是走的时候
were they coming or going?
无法判断
It was impossible to say.
根本没有任何轮廓
There was never any outline.
到现在居然还在刮风下雨
Pouring rain and blowing a hurricane ever since.
现在那些足迹将会比手稿更难认了
They'll be harder to read now than the palimpsest.
那么警督 在你确定
So inspector, what did you do
你没有确定任何事情之后
after you made certain
你做了什么呢
that you've made certain of nothing?
说真的 福尔摩斯先生
Well really, Mr. Holmes,
我认为我做得够好了
I think I made certain of a good deal.
有人小心地从屋外
Somebody had entered the house
进了房子
cautiously from without.
然后还有那个男的临死前说的话
And then there were the dying man's own words.
最后
And finally,
在他紧握的右手里
there was a very important piece of evidence
发现了一个非常重要的证据
found clasped in his right hand.
Willoughby Smith视力很好
Willoughby Smith had excellent sight.
毫无疑问
There can be no question
这个是从凶手的脸上
that these were snatched from the face
夺下来的
or the person of the assassin.
你要找的是个女人
The person you seek is a woman,
Mycroft
Mycroft.
那可以从眼镜的精致推断出
That can be inferred from their delicacy,
当然
and also, of course,
也可以从那男人的临终话语推断出
from the last words of the dying man,
镜框用黄金裱得非常漂亮
they're handsomely mounted in solid gold.
镜片的度数很高
They are of unusual strength,
她肯定非常近视
she must have appalling eyesight,
一个因长期用眼
a lady whose vision
而视力极度下降的 女人
has been so extremely contracted for any great length of time
应该会有以下的
would surely carry physical characteristics
相貌特征
of such vision.
有皱纹的前额
Puckered forehead,
眼神木纳
peering expression,
削肩
rounded shoulders.
这副眼镜最近还被修过
They've also recently been repaired.
当然 我会计划去伦敦的眼镜商那里转转
Of course, I'd intended to go the round of the London opticians.
早上6点有列从Charing Cross
There's a train from Charing Cross to Chatham
开往Chathamat的火车 福尔摩斯先生
at 6:00 in the morning, Mr. Holmes.
那我得搭那列车
Then I shall take it.
还有更多有关这个案件的情况 要告诉我们吗 警督
Have you anything more to tell us about the case inspector?
我认为你现在了解的跟我一样多
I think you know as much as I do now,
也许更多
perhaps more.
也许
Perhaps,
perhaps.
让我感到困惑的
What puzzles me
是这个案件里完全没有动机
is the utter want of all object in the crime.
一个男的被残忍地谋杀了 福尔摩斯先生
A man has been cruelly murdered, Mr. Holmes,
但没有人能讲出其中的动机
and not a ghost of a motive can anyone suggest.
是谁向当地警察报的警
Who alerted their local police?
Mortimer 那个园丁 他是无辜的
Mortimer, the gardener, an innocent.
当了解到这个案子
As soon as it became clear
属于苏格兰场管辖
that it was a matter for Scotland Yard,
上面便派我去做调查
the chief constable sent for me.
抱歉 先生 那里不能进
Sorry, sir, can't go in there.
请这边走
Just walk this way please.
没关系 警官 这些人是我带来的
It's all right constable, these gentlemen are with me.
除了这个致命的裁纸刀
Apart from this lethal paper knife
和夹鼻眼镜
and the pince-nez,
从昨天早上开始 这个房间里的其他东西
has anything been rearranged
有被重新整理过或是被挪动过吗
or removed in this room since yesterday morning?
没有 福尔摩斯先生 现场和当时一模一样
No, Mr. Holmes. Everything is exactly as it was.
尸体呢
And the body?
尸体倒在这里
The body fell here.
伤口在脖子的右侧
The wound was in the right side of the neck,
从后面穿到前面
from behind, forwards.
非常好 警督
Excellent inspector,
那这个办公桌?
and this bureau?
教授向我保证没有丢任何东西
The professor assures me that nothing is missing.
我很庆幸没有发生抢劫
I'm satisfied that no robbery has taken place.
你为什么没跟我提到这个划痕 Hopkins
Why did you not tell me about this scratch, Hopkins?
当然我注意到了
Well I noticed it of course,
但你总能在锁孔周围找到划痕
but you'll always find scratches around a keyhole.
看起来很新
It looks recent.
非常新
Very recent.
油漆也被划掉了
There's the varnish, too,
就像是犁沟两边的泥土
like earth on either side of a furrow.
那很重要吗
Is it significant?
那是父亲的放大镜
That's father's magnifying glass.
是的
Yes.
他给你了
He gave it to you?
真够讽刺的 请让一让
How ironic, excuse me.
在Willoughby Smith和凶手之前
Who was the last person to enter this room
谁是最后进这个房间的人
before Willoughby Smith and his murderer?
是我
I was.
Marker夫人
Mrs. Marker.
那个女管家
The housekeeper.
是的 请坐
Yes, please sit down.
谢谢 我宁愿站着
Thank you, I prefer to stand.
你也许听说过Sherlock 福尔摩斯先生
You've probably heard of Mr. Sherlock Holmes?
没有
No.
那并不重要
It's really not important.
在Willoughby Smith被谋杀前 你在这个房间待过?
You were in this room before Willoughby Smith was murdered?
大概一刻钟前
About a quarter of an hour before.
为什么
Why?
我是女管家 福尔摩斯先生
I am the housekeeper, Mr. Holmes.
我得保持书房尽可能的干净整洁
I try to keep the study as clean and as tidy as possible,
而不是你所注意到的那些不同之处
not that you'd notice the difference.
你是一个人在这里的吗
Were you alone in here?
我是一个人
I was alone.
我从不在教授工作的时候到这里来
I never come in here when the professor's at work.
据我所知
As far as I know,
Smith先生当时正在楼上的房间里
Mr. Smith was upstairs in his room at the time.
那你根本就没见过他
So you didn't see him at all?
直到他...
Not until after he...
他被...
he was...
被...
been...
当时我已经把这里打扫完了
I'd finished my housework in here
正在准备教授的午餐
and I was preparing the professor's lunch
这时我听见...
when I heard...
当我到达书房时
By the time I reached the study,
Smith先生死了
Mr. Smith was dead.
那很明显你错过了他临死前所说的话
Then you were obviously too late to hear his last words?
除了那声惨叫我没听见别的东西
I heard nothing except that dreadful cry.
醒醒 警官
Wake up, constable.
那之后你干什么了
What did you do then?
我直接去了教授的房间
I went straight to the professor's room.
他被吓坏了
He was horribly agitated.
那声惨叫让他知道
He'd heard enough to know
有可怕的事情发生了
that something terrible had happened.
你今天早晨给这张办公桌掸灰了吗
Did you dust this bureau this morning?
是的
I did.
那你注意到锁旁边的擦痕了吗
Did you observe the scratch by the lock?
没有
I did not.
你当然没有了 Marker夫人
Of course you didn't, Mrs. Marker.
你的掸子已经把
Your duster would have swept away
那些油漆碎片掸掉了
those scraps of varnish.
钥匙在哪里
And where's the key?
教授把它挂在了表链上
The professor keeps it on his watch chain.
-不论什么时候? -不论什么时候
-At all times? -At all times.
很好 很好 很好
Good, good, good,
-我们有进展了 -谢谢你 Marker夫人
-we're making progress. -Thank you Mrs. Marker.
能麻烦你让女仆到书房来一下吗
Would you be so good as to ask the housemaid to come along to the study?
当然 警督
Certainly inspector.
让我们看看
Let us see,
这张桌子能告诉我们什么
what this desk reveals.
哦 Mycroft 这很有趣
Uh, Mycroft, this is interesting.
那是什么
What is it?
Willoughby Smith手写的今天的记录
An entry for today in Willoughby Smith's handwriting.
修道院 7:30
Abbey, 7:30,
真奇怪
how curious.
我想我能为你解释那个 先生
I think I can answer that one for you, sir.
Coram教授正在写一本
Professor Coram is writing a book
有关早期基督异教徒的书
about early Christian heretics.
并且这所房子附近
And there are a number of Abbey ruins
有一些修道院的废墟
within reasonable traveling distance of the house.
修道院 7:30 为什么是7:30
Abbey, 7:30, why 7:30?
Tarlton小姐 请到这里来
Miss Tarlton, please come here.
请坐
Please sit down.
福尔摩斯先生是一位伦敦来的侦探
Mr. Holmes is a detective from London.
你能告诉他 昨天早上的所见所闻吗
Would you tell him everything you saw and heard yesterday morning?
当时十一二点的样子
It was between 11:00 and 12:00.
Coram教授还躺在床上
Professor Coram was still in bed.
当天气不好时 他很少在正午前起床
When the weather is poor he seldom rises before midday.
Marker夫人正在厨房里忙家务
Mrs. Marker was busy with some work in the kitchen.
那么
So.
现在你可以看着我
Now you can look at me.
那当时你在哪里
So where were you?
那时我正在楼上的一间卧室里挂窗帘
I was hanging some curtains in one of the bedrooms upstairs.
Smith先生在他自己的房间里
Mr. Smith had been in his own room.
过了一会儿我听见他穿过走廊
At that moment I heard him walk along the passage
下楼去了书房
and descend to the study.
你怎么这么肯定 那就是Willoughby Smith
How can you be sure that is was Willoughby Smith?
因为他的脚步声很熟悉 先生
Because he had a familiar tread, sir.
我没有听见书房的关门声
I didn't hear the study door close.
过了一两分钟
About a minute or so later
便传来了一声惨叫
there came a dreadful cry.
那是令人毛骨悚然的尖叫
It was a wild horrid scream,
那么的奇怪和反常
so strange and unnatural.
无法辨别发出那声音的是男还是女
It could have come either from a man or a woman.
我跑下来 去了书房
I ran down to the study.
发现Willoughby躺在了地上
Found Willoughby lying on the floor.
我看见了血
Saw the blood,
我没有意识到
I didn't realize,
他一定死了
he must be dead.
然后他说话了
And then he spoke.
是她
It was she.
教授 是她
Professor, it was she.
是的
Yes.
好奇怪的话
Curious words.
你知道这是什么意思吗
Do you know what they mean?
不知道 先生
No, sir.
你确定?
Are you sure?
不知道 先生
No, sir.
在你听到惨叫后
Could anyone have left by the rear exit
有人从后门离开过吗
after the time you'd heard the scream?
你是说在我下楼前
You mean before I got down the stairs,
那我应该会在走廊看见他
I'd have seen them in the passage.
并且后门从没打开过
And the backdoor never opened
否则我会听见的
or I would have heard it.
谢谢你 Tarlton小姐
Thank you, Miss Tarlton,
Mycroft 警督
Mycroft, inspector.
或许他是因为跟爱人吵架而被害
Perhaps he was the victim of a lover's quarrel?
那他死得真不值
How very tiresome for the man.
快中午了
It's nearly midday.
教授还待在他的卧室里吗
Will the professor still be in his room?
是的 他从昨天早上开始还没离开过那里
Yes, he hasn't left it since yesterday morning.
那你得跟我介绍介绍
Then you must introduce me.
怎么了 福尔摩斯先生
What is it, Mr. Holmes?
两条走廊都是铺的椰衣垫 (椰子壳纤维编成的垫子)
Both corridors are lined with coconut matting.
我注意到了
I've noticed.
谢谢你 先生
Thank you, sir.
这跟案子有什么关系呢
What of it.
那似乎对我很有启发性
It seems to me to be suggestive.
不见得吧
Indeed.
请进
Come.
关上门 Hopkins
Close the door, Hopkins.
寒冷的空气对我的支气管炎没好处
The cold air won't help my bronchial condition.
你们其中一个肯定是夏洛克 福尔摩斯
One of you gentlemen must be Sherlock Holmes.
这是我的哥哥 Mycroft
This is my brother, Mycroft.
你抽烟吗 福尔摩斯先生
Are you a smoker, Mr. Holmes?
抽烟是我唯一的陋习
I have few other vices.
啊 亚历山大烟草
Uh, Alexandrian.
-是的 请抽一支 -谢谢
-Yes, Pray take a cigarette. -Thank you.
它们是由lonides为我特别准备的
I have them especially prepared by lonides.
每次给我送来1000支
Sends me 1,000 at a time.
我很苦恼不得不每隔两周
I grieve to say that I have to arrange
安排一次新的送货
a fresh supply every fortnight.
你呢 先生
You sir?
不 谢了 不 我更喜欢这个
No, thank you, no, I prefer this.
烟草和工作
Tobacco and my work,
我只剩下这些了
that's all there is left of me,
烟草和工作
tobacco and my work.
现在 只有烟草
Now, only tobacco.
谁能预见如此可怕的灾难
Who could have foreseen such a terrible catastrophe?
我向你保证 福尔摩斯先生
I assure you, Mr. Holmes,
在仅仅几个月的训练后
that after, what, just a few months, training,
他就成为了一个非常好的助手
he was an admirable assistant.
对这个案子你有什么看法
What do you think of the matter, hey?
我还没有理出头绪来
I have not yet made up my mind.
我会对你很感激的
I would indeed be indebted to you
如果你能在黑暗中
if you could throw a light
给我们带来一丝曙光
on all that is dark to us,
对于像我这样一个半瘫痪的可怜的
such a blow, paralyzing to a poor, old bookworm,
病弱的老书呆子也算是一种慰藉
invalid, like myself.
你不能继续写你的著作吗 教授
Could you not continue with your work, professor?
哎呀 福尔摩斯先生
Alas Mr. Holmes,
我似乎失去了思考的能力
I seem to have lost the faculty of thought.
哦 天哪
Oh dear.
我最伟大的作品
My magnum opus,
对在叙利亚和埃及的
my analysis of documents
埃及土人的修道院内
found in the Coptic monasteries
找到的文件进行分析
of Syria and Egypt.
我希望能够 在现有的宗教基础上深入研究
It is a work that I hoped to have cut deep at the very foundations of revealed religion.
这真令人叹为观止
This looks impressive.
但我的健康每况愈下
But with my enfeebled health,
我不知道
I don't know that I shall
在没有助手的情况下
ever be able to complete it,
还能不能把它写完
without my assistant.
我不想用什么冗长的调查
I don't want to trouble you
来打扰你
with a lengthy examination.
简单地说
Simply,
我只想问你 Willoughby Smith的遗言
to ask you what Willoughby Smith
是什么意思
meant by his last words,
"教授 是她"
"The professor, it was she?"
Susan
Susan,
一个乡村姑娘 福尔摩斯先生
a country girl, Mr. Holmes.
你一定注意到了那个阶级
You must be aware of the incredible stupidity
令人难以置信的愚蠢
of that class.
设想一下 我那可怜的助手 低声说了一些不连贯的话
I fancy the poor fellow murmured some incoherent words
而她硬把它们组成毫无意义的信息
and she twisted them into a meaningless message.
对于这场悲剧 你对自己的名字 出现在遗言里就没有任何解释?
You have no explanation yourself for the tragedy?
可能吧
Possibly.
下面的话我只想在我们之间说
I breathe this only among ourselves.
可能是自杀
Possibly suicide.
自杀
Suicide.
年轻人有他们所不为人知的麻烦 福尔摩斯先生
Young men have their hidden troubles, Mr. Holmes,
或许是感情破裂的问题
an affair of the heart perhaps,
这些是我们不可能知道的
which we will never know.
这是一种比谋杀更有可能的假设
It's a more probable supposition than murder.
那夹鼻眼镜又作何解释
And what of the pince-nez?
一把扇子 一只手套 一副眼镜
A fan, a glove, eye-glasses
谁知道人临死前会带着什么
who knows what article may be carried as a token
纪念品或是值钱的东西吧
or treasured when a man puts an end to his life.
我得离开这里了
I must get out of here.
也许我说话像个小孩子
Possibly I speak as a child,
但在我看来 Willoughby Smith是自杀的
seems to me Willoughby Smith met his fate by his own hand.
Willoughby Smith是被谋杀的 他没有自杀
Willoughby Smith was murdered. He did not commit suicide.
下午好 先生
Good afternoon, sir.
是的 我同意
Yes, I agree.
那教授所说的对这个案子毫无帮助
So the professor's theory has no bearing on the case.
能麻烦你
Will you be good enough
替我安排马车
to arrange carriage and escort for me
和火车的行程吗
as far as the railway station?
当然 先生
Of course, sir.
我得回去一趟 所以我会带你一起走
I have to get back to town so I'll take you there myself.
你真是太好了
You're very kind.
我认为你会觉得
I think you might find
这比亚历山大烟草
this more beneficial
更有用
than Alexandrian tobacco.
你还记得在我们年轻的时候
Do you remember what papa used to tell us
父亲是怎么教导我们的?
when we were young?
除去不可能的
Eliminate the impossible
不管剩下什么
and whatever remains,
也不管剩下的如何不大可能
however improbable,
那一定就是真相
must be the truth.
我忘了他的原话
I forget his exact words
但我说的基本接近
but those are near enough.
回头见
See you in London.
Ionides (一个俄国人名)
Ionides.
我没注意到一些事
I'm overlooking something,
但它就在我眼前
and it's staring me in the face.
哦 谢谢你
Oh, thank you my dear.
坏消息 先生
Bad news I'm afraid, sir.
直到今天很晚才有
There isn't another train for Charing Cross
去Charing Cross的火车
till late this evening.
你应该在把我拽到这里来之前
You should double-check the railway timetable
仔细检查火车时刻表
before dragging me to this wretched place.
我知道 先生 抱歉 先生
I know sir and I'm sorry sir.
等一下 警督
Just a minute, inspector.
我们可以等会儿回伦敦
London can wait.
我认为我们应该推迟我们行程
I think we should postpone our trip for a little while
去参加一个政治集会
to attend a political meeting.
我们总是听到改革改革
We hear of reform after reform.
我们不该支持这些女性 福尔摩斯先生
We shouldn't encourage these women, Mr. Holmes.
她们是闹事者 比罪犯好不到哪儿去
They're troublemakers, no better then criminals.
组织者 Abigail Grosby小姐
Organizer, Miss Abigail Grosby
7点半
meeting held in the church hall
在教堂集会
at half past 7:00.
想想吧 警督
Think back inspector,
Willoughby Smith的日记
Willoughby Smith's diaries,
修道院 7:30
Abbey 7:30.
你能小声点吗
Do you mind?
感谢你们如此的敏锐
Thank you gentlemen for your sensitivity.
我们总是听到改革改革
We hear of reform after reform
但仍然没有采取任何措施
and yet still nothing is done
来提高女性的社会地位
to improve the position of women in society.
我们国家的命运
The fate of our country
仍然只是由男性来决定
is still being decided by men alone
而女性
and yet women,
在法律上
who are subjected daily and equally
具有同等的地位
to the laws of the land,
却不允许投票
are not permitted to vote.
那一定是Abigail Grosby小姐
That must be Miss Abigail Grosby,
真可怕
formidable.
女性选举权
Votes for women indeed,
接下来是什么
whatever next,
女警察
women police,
女政治家?
women politicians?
我再次警告你
I'm not going to tell you again.
女权解放运动
The struggle for female enfranchisement
-至今都是以和平的方式进行 -上帝禁止这些
-has so far beena peaceful one. -God forbid.
时机成熟了 我们必须扪心自问
The time has come and we must ask ourselves
这个国家还会像这样持续多久
how much longer the state of affairs can continue?
我们还应该忍受
How much longer we should allow ourselves
二等公民的待遇多久
to be treated like second-class citizens?
你告诉他们吧 Abigail
You tell them Abigail.
扯淡
Poppycock.
我想给你们读一封
I'd like to read you a letter
我两天前收到的
which I received two days ago
来自Garrett Fawcett夫人的信
from Mrs. Garrett Fawcett,
她敦促我们继续斗争
urging us to continue the fight
直到实现目标
until we achieve our aims.
那应该会让你感兴趣的 警督
That should interest you, inspector.
哦 哦 哦
Well, well, well.
Mycroft
Mycroft.
在各个领域
On every side,
那些有能力帮助的人
those in a position to help,
全都装聋作哑
are stricken by deafness.
我们被告知这个国家
We're told that the country
有比女性选举权更重要的事需要担心
has more important things to worry about than votes for women.
那告诉我
Yet tell me,
还有什么比占总人口数一半的人的权利更重要
what can be more important than the rights of half of the population?
已故的的女王不也是个女人吗
Was the late queen not also a woman?
我已经忍了这些犯罪课堂一天了 警督
I have had quite enough of the criminal classes for one day, inspector.
你给我约的那辆马车在哪里
Where's that carriage you promised me?
我真的一无所知 先生
I don't know nothing about nothing, sir, honest.
那你干吗哭呢 Tarlton小姐
Then why are you crying Miss Tarlton?
因为我不想惹上麻烦
Cause I don't want to be in no trouble.
否则我会丢了工作
I'll lose my situation if I do.
我再问你一次
I'll ask you one more time,
Willoughby Smith是不是认识
was Willoughby Smith acquainted with
那个叫Abigail Grosby的女教师
the schoolteacher Miss Abigail Grosby?
我不知道
I don't know.
你知道的 Tarlton小姐
You do know Miss Tarlton.
撒谎是没用的
It's useless to lie.
是的 他是认识
Yes, he was.
他们互相认识
They knew each other all right.
他们是情人
They had a blazing row.
Abbey 请你听我说
Abbey, will you listen to me please.
前天
Day before yesterday.
你正在为这些选举权 浪费你的时间
You're wasting your time on these suffrages.
难道你看不出来吗
Don't you see that?
谢谢 Willoughby
Thank you, Willoughby.
你的支持真是一如既往的势不可挡
Your support is overwhelming as ever.
他说他爱我
He said he loved me.
照顾我
Take care of me,
而我相信了他
and I believed him.
-别碰我 -Abby Abby Abby
-Don't you touch me. -Abby, Abby, Abby.
-别碰我 -好的 好的
-Don't touch me. -All right, all right.
我只是想让你理智一点
I'm just trying to make you see reason.
你整天和这些几乎不认识的人在一起
You're spending your time with these people you barely know
你应该跟我一起生活
when you should be building a life with me.
放手
Take your hands off.
上帝都知道她们中有一半 是最最低劣的
God knows half of them are the lowest of the low.
你不该跟这些人混在一起
These are not the sort of people that you should be mixing with.
这是我的生活
This is my life.
我要做什么
What I choose to do with it
要跟什么人一起做都是我的事情
and who I choose to do it with is my business.
没人能阻止我
No one is going to stand in my way.
我说明白了吗
Do I make myself clear?
如果那是你所想要的话
If that's what you want.
我很确切地知道我想要什么
I know exactly what I want
但此时此刻并不包括你
and at the moment it doesn't include you.
是女权解放运动让你这么想的 是不是
That's what emancipation does for a woman, is it?
你喝酒了
You've been drinking.
我告诉过你喝酒后
I've told you not to come near me
别靠近我的
when you've been drinking.
它让你拒绝了我的求婚
Makes you turn down a good offer of marriage,
一次可以真正快乐的机会
a chance to be really happy
却成为了一个不幸的 好卖弄学问的女人
instead of a miserable blue stocking.
你最好离开
You'd better leave.
是空的
It's empty.
我认为你会觉得
I think you might find this more beneficial
这比亚历山大烟草更管用
than Alexandrian tobacco.
她的视力良好
Nothing wrong with her sight.
Abigail Grosby小姐
Miss Abigail Grosby,
Crosby小姐
Miss Crosby,
夏洛克 福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Sherlock Holmes.
警督无疑已经向你解释了目前的状况
The inspector has no doubt explained state of things to you
那你应该知道你的不利处境
then you know the seriousness of your position.
你有什么要为自己辩护的吗
Do you have anything to say in your defense?
只有那个我被指控的 莫须有的罪名
Only that I am innocent of the crime of which I am accused.
但你知道他死了
But you did know the deceased?
那也算是犯罪?
Is that also a crime?
我们曾是很亲密的朋友 直到...
We were close friends until...
直到?
Until?
我在他心目中的位置 比他在我心目中的位置要重要的多
I meant more to him than he did to me.
我现在意识到了这一点
I realize that now.
但无论如何
But for all the world
我都不希望他受到伤害
I would not have wished him any harm.
警督告诉我
The inspector informed me
你跟Willoughby Smith
that you had a violent quarrel with Willoughby Smith
在他死的前一天吵得很凶
the day before he died?
双方的谈吐都很粗鲁
There were harsh words spoken on both sides,
但有很好的理由
but with good reason.
你或许知道我是个 女性选举权运动的积极份子
You probably know that I'm an active member of the women's suffrage movement.
Willoughby认为
Willoughby believed, selfishly I think,
我在拿自己未来的生活和自由冒险
that my future way of life
但我认为那是他自私的想法
and my liberty were at great risk.
我再次向他保证 我们在这里的运动
I reassured him that our campaign here
是尽可能地以和平的方式进行的
was as peaceful as may be.
我不想为了改变法律 而违反它
I have no wish to break the law in order to change it,
除非...
unless...
关于你在书房的办公桌
Regarding, your bureau in the study,
那里面有什么东西
does it contain anything
是别人想偷的吗
which someone might wish to steal?
据我所知没有值钱的东西
Nothing of value that I know of,
我妻子寄过来的家书
family papers and letters from my poor wife,
值得我骄傲的大学毕业证书
diplomas from universities that have done me honor.
这是钥匙 你可以自己去看
Have the key, you can look for yourself.
鼻烟
Snuff.
你的午餐 教授
Your lunch professor.
不饿吗 福尔摩斯先生
Not hungry, Mr. Holmes?
那些香烟可不会提高你的食欲
Those cigarettes don't help your appetite.
无疑出于同样的原因
For the same reason no doubt
教授也没吃多少东西
that the professor returns to the kitchen,
而把更多的送回了厨房
more food than he eats.
我可以认为
Am I to assume
有进一步进展了是吗 警督
there have been further developments, inspector?
我是这么被告知的 教授
So I'm told, professor.
很遗憾 福尔摩斯先生
I fail to see, Mr. Holmes,
我无法再给予你进一步的帮助
how I can be of any further assistance to you.
我把我所知道的每一个环节
I forged and tested
都串起来了 Coram教授
every link of my chain, Professor Coram,
并且我肯定这就是真相
and I'm sure that it is sound.
他到底在胡说些什么
What on earth is he talking about?
两天前
Two days ago,
一个女人进了你的书房
a woman entered your study.
她来的目的很明确
She came with express intention
就是要拿走你办公桌里的某些文件
of taking certain papers, which were held in your bureau.
她有一把自己的钥匙
She had a key of her own.
你自己的钥匙上并没有
Your own key doesn't have that slight discoloration,
刮掉油漆后所留下的小斑点
which the scratch made upon the varnish would have produced.
这不是在诋毁你
She came, as far as my evidence can tell me,
但她来过
without your knowledge,
正如我的证据所显示的那样
to rob you.
既然现在你已经追查出这位女士了
Now surely having traced this lady so far,
那你也能告诉我她后来怎么样了
you can also say what has since become of her?
我会尽力那么做的
I shall endeavor to do so.
首先 她被你的秘书抓住了
In the first place, she was seized by your secretary.
她为了逃走而刺伤了他
She stabbed him in order to escape.
那是个不幸的意外
It was an unhappy accident,
但我确信那位女士并无意
but I am convinced that the lady had no intention
想杀害他
of inflicting so grievous an injury.
由于被她的所为吓坏了
Horrified by what she had done,
她匆忙地逃离了案发现场
she rushed wildly away from the scene of the tragedy.
但不幸的是
Unfortunately for her,
她在扭打中丢失了她的夹鼻眼镜
she lost her pince-nez in the scuffle.
她跑过走廊
She ran down the corridor,
本该是从来的那条路逃走的
which she imagined to be that by which she had come.
但两条走廊铺的都是椰衣垫
Both were lined with coconut matting.
当她发现自己走错了的时候
Only when it was too late,
已经太晚了
did she understand that she had taken the wrong passage
因为她回去的路被切断了
and that her retreat was cut off.
她该怎么办
What was she to do?
她不能往回走
She could not go back.
她也不能待在走廊里
She could not remain where she was.
她必须继续往前走
She must go on.
她继续走
She went on.
非常好 福尔摩斯先生
All very fine, Mr. Holmes.
你是不是想说我躺在床上
Do you want me to say that I could lie in that bed
没有注意到
and not be aware
一个陌生的女人进了我的房间?
that a strange woman had entered my room?
你当然注意到她了 教授
Of course you were aware of her professor.
你从这些烟雾中就认出她了
You recognized her through this haze of your existence.
-你跟她讲话了 -你疯了
-You spoke with her. -You're mad.
-你帮助她躲过了警察 -你在说疯话
-You helped her to elude the police. -You're talking insanely.
我帮助她躲过了警察?
I helped her to elude the police?
那她现在在哪里
Well where is she now?
这里 她一直待的地方
Here, where she has been all along.
你是对的
You are right,
you're right.
我在这里
I am here.
我能听见一切
I could hear everything
我知道你已经了解了真相
and I know that you have learned the truth.
你说那是个意外是对的
But you were right to say it was an accident.
我不知道手里拿的是裁纸刀
I did not know it was a knife in my hand.
当时感到绝望的我
For in my despair,
会抓起任何东西
I snatched at anything
打晕他 让他放我走
and struck at him to make him let me go.
我只剩下一点时间了
I have only a little time here
我会让你知道全部的事实
and I would have, that you know the whole truth.
我是这个男人的妻子
That I am this man's wife.
他不是英国人
He's not an Englishman.
他是俄国人
He's a Russian.
你为什么如此地渴望
Why should you cling so hard
你那令人作呕的生活 Sergius
to that retched life of yours, Sergius?
你伤害了太多人
It has done harm to so many
没有人从中受益
and good to none,
甚至你自己也没有
not even yourself.
当我们在圣彼得堡结婚的时候 你50岁了
You were 50 and I, a young girl,
而我还是个年轻的姑娘
when we married in St. Petersburg.
我那么地爱你
I loved you so much.
比那更甚
More then that,
我极度崇拜你
I idolized you.
我会为你做任何事 并且我也那样做了
I would have done anything for you, and I did.
因为那时你是我的一切
Because then you were everything to me.
但我们是改革家
But we were reformers,
虚无主义者
Nihilists,
很快大麻烦就来了
and soon there came a time of great trouble.
Sergius
Sergius!
不 Sergius
No, Sergius
不能再有伤亡了
no more deaths
不要再有了
no more.
Sergius
Sergius!
Sergius在哪里
Where's Sergius?
忘了你的丈夫吧
Forget your husband.
他背叛了我们所有人
He has betrayed us all.
-不 -是的 Anna
-No. -Yes, Anna.
我们被背叛了
We are betrayed.
我们因为你的招供全被抓了起来
We were all arrested upon your confession.
我们中的一些人被判处绞刑
Some of us went to the gallows
而另外一些被流放到了西伯利亚
and some of us to Siberia.
过了20年我才被释放
After 20 years I was released.
你带着你那血腥钱来到了英国
You came to England with your blood money
从此过着宁静的生活
and lived in quiet ever since.
据我所知
Knowing well,
只要组织一旦找到你在哪里
that if the brotherhood ever found out where you were
不出一个星期
not a week would pass
你将会受到公正的裁决
before justice would be done.
我就在你手上 Anna
I'm in your hands, Anna.
你总是对我那么好
You were always good to me.
我的弟弟Alexis
My brother, Alexis,
是个高尚无私的人
was noble, unselfish.
他讨厌暴力
He hated violence
还写了很多信
and wrote many letters
试图劝阻我们不要继续下去
trying to dissuade us from such a course.
这些信将会证明他是无辜的
These letters would have proved his innocence
而你把它们从我这里偷走藏起来了
and you stole them from me and hid them.
所以Alexis被流放到了西伯利亚
So Alexis was sent to Siberia
至今还被关在那里
where he is even now.
我的刑期一满
As soon as my time of imprisonment is over,
我就决定取回
I determined to get the letters
那些能释放我弟弟的信
that would procure my brother's release.
我知道我的丈夫来到了英国
I knew that my husband had come to England
在好几个月的调查后
and after many months of searching
我确定了你在哪里
I determined where he was.
所以最后我决定自己取回那些信件
So at last I determined to get the letters for myself.
我才刚刚把它们从办公桌里拿出来
I had just removed them from the bureau
这时那个年轻人抓住了我
when the young man seized me,
那天早上早些时候我还遇到了他
the same young man I had met earlier that morning.
我问他Coram教授住在哪里
I had asked him where Professor Coram lived
但并不知道他就在他手下工作
not knowing that he worked for him.
那他也一定跟教授谈到了你
And he must have told the professor about you.
教授 是她
The professor, it was she.
在他倒下后
When he had fallen,
我跑了 但我走错了门
I ran but I went to the wrong door
来到了他的房间
and found myself in his room.
你 你说要把我供出去
You, you talked of giving me up.
我告诉过你 如果你那么做
I showed you that if you did so
我就毁了你的生活
your life was in my hands.
如果你把我交给警察
If you gave me to the law
我就把你交给组织
I could give you to the Brotherhood.
那样我们的生命 就首次在婚后有了羁绊
That as our liveshad once been bound together in marriage.
我们的命运也因此 永远交织在一起
So our destinies would forever be entwined.
(俄语)
(Speaking Russian).
结束了
It is finished.
也绝不会开始
It never began.
你的饭菜被送到了这里
You had your meals sent in here
那样她就能跟你一起吃
so she could share your food.
你们俩达成协议 当警察离开后
It was agreed that when the police left
她就趁着夜色逃走
that she should slip away into the night
并再也不相见
and never be seen again.
这些信可以救我弟弟
These are the letters that will save my brother's life.
把它们送去俄国大使馆
Take them to the Russian embassy.
毒药
Poison.
一封手写的信 福尔摩斯先生
A letter by hand, Mr. Holmes.
谢谢你 Hudson夫人
Thank you Mrs. Hudson,
睡个好觉
sleep well.
很明显 从眼镜的度数来看
It was clear to me from the strength of the spectacles
如果被弄丢了 其佩带者必定跟瞎了一般
that the wearer must have been almost blind without them.
因此我作出了
And I therefore considered the hypothesis
她仍留在房子里的假设
that she remained within the house.
你也许会说这很容易想到
You might say it was elementary.
哦 对了
Oh, by the way,
别跟华生提起鼻烟的事
don't mention the snuff to Watson.
告诉他你故意掉下了 一些烟灰或什么东西
Tell him you dropped a cigarette ash or something.
别让我惹上麻烦
Leave me out of it.
但到底为什么 那位令人作呕的女人
But why on earth did the retched woman
不得不自杀呢
feel compelled to take her own life?
她达到了她的目的
She'd achieved her purpose,
毫无希望并且深处绝望之中
past hope and in despair,
当然还有为爱殉情
and the death of love, of course.
哦 教授
Oh, professor,
望你罪有应得
be sure your sin will find you out.